bante can the practice of observing my
mind lead to the right
view just I sit down well depends I
watch my mind if it is the actual mind
that you observing or is it your idea of
the mind that you're observing
MH if it's the actual mind
then no well you you can't just observe your
no well you you can't just observe your
mind and expect to learn from it you
need to
know um what that mind is you need to see
um what that mind is you need to see
what makes it Wilder what tames it you
need to endure its bursts and outfits
and irrational episodes they're trying
to make you
act and then you can see through what
you need to see sure but if you just
think by watching what I think the mind
is and somehow the truth will magically
reveal itself that's not going to happen
you it's like you're starting off with
this idea that you already know what the
mind is and well yeah exactly that's all
for for for many people that's already a
problem yeah that's a yeah
exactly and is it is there a
practical uh difference between like in
Pary you have these different terms of
chitt Mano viyana so mind there's
thinking intellect
intellect
Consciousness yeah so what is the mind
you know what's the Mind part is it is
it all just the same thing it's not
refering referring to the same thing
but defining it in terms of further
ideas will not necessarily make it any
clearer I mean it might make you
think you now see the difference between
the three things but practically if you
don't see your mind you see Nether
there so Mano is your intellect it's
your rational thought it's your ability
to think think that actively thinking
thoughts engages your Mana chitt is um
well the translation the old translation
was heart so say when you're practicing
self reflection self-awareness awareness
of you in your situation of your mind
being engaged with of your Mano being
engaged with this and that so that's CH
it's kind of a more General
uh mental mood that also encompasses
your physicality it's not separate from
it you won't find your mood somewhere
else from where your body is either
you're going to be there and you're
going to feel it in your body as
well so that's that's what chitt is so
the the general mood SL
feeling that's kind
of revealed however obscurely but to
some extent in revealed in an act of
self-reflection so in an act of stepping
back from what your senses and your Mano
are directly engaged
with so becoming aware of you thinking
these thoughts or you seeing these SES
not seeing SES me see
SES SES that's that's that's what
occupies my attention but now through
practice of self-reflection you
recognize yourself in the situation of
being preoccupied with the sight so it's
kind of a way of stepping back in that
direction where you're going to find the
state of that chitt whether it's related
depressed expanded narrowed heavy light
all these descriptions in the sutas
that's what it applies to it's kind of
on that level of the mood and how things
are but that level the current situation
that level most people don't see that
that's too subtle in any a way well it's
it's there perpetually available there
yeah it's not it's not mysteriously sort
of uh hidden that you don't know where
to look but people don't know how to
recognize it and stay with it and then
discern it further they might get a hint
of it and then fall into the ideas about
it the description Overlook it or
underlook it like you get a sense of it
but then you look away you prioritize
your thoughts of your mood of your
enduring situation at the expense of the
mood and the enduring situation that's
still they
unchanged and a Consciousness
then well Consciousness on the level of
the Aggregates so I really wouldn't
worry about you will not even be able to
intellectually grasp it correctly unless
you already have a good grasp of your CH
for what it is it's just going to you're
just going to have your idea of your of
your chart made connections between the
Aggregates and philosophical and
psychological ideas
and that won't be Consciousness those be
ideas that you're conscious
of see saying like oh you are conscious
off like in philosophy we talked about
Consciousness it's the approximation of
Consciousness but Consciousness is not
something you do you are the result of
Consciousness being there as one of the
Aggregates so I am conscious of kind of
implies you being on one end from which
Consciousness originates and and it's
being sent to these directions but it's
completely around any notion of
around any notion of
space uh uh your sense of self
everything else in between is because
Consciousness is already
there so when you would have if you
would have purified everything else from
your wrong assumptions of ownership
permanence what's left there of that
experience that's what Consciousness is
the presence of those unobscured things
so the I think for somebody at the stage
of development the closest they could be
thinking about Consciousness rightly
would not be uh in terms of thinking
about the ideas of Consciousness but we
ex it would be on the level of exactly
becoming a aware of your situation
unabsorbed from any of the six senses
not denying what your six senses are
occupied with just putting that in
certain like a like a at a certain arms
length that's revealed in that
self-reflection so the experience of
that then once say you become accustomed
to that practice of correct mindfulness
really it's nothing else of of un
absorbing yourself to the right extent
not to the extent that you then get
absorbed in your new ideas float away
and float away in something else yeah
unabsorbed just to the extent you were
absorbed but then leave it being there
um
the practice of that then you can have
these other ideas sort of um come out of
it so to speak like for example the
assumption that as I said that you are
at this end of Consciousness that
Consciousness originates from
here that you are doing the
Consciousness that you are the conscious
one all all these that Consciousness is
in your
brain then you realize what
Consciousness is in my brain which is
another image I'm conscious of right
here now as a thinking that so you
realize there is no standpoint outside
of Consciousness that you can take from
which Consciousness can be related to
and clarifying that would be clarifying
the wrong Notions that kind of linger
around the view in regard to
Consciousness such as Consciousness is
mine I am Consciousness it's in me and
all of those Appropriations and that's
why that's important to eventually
discern is because through those
overlooking and kind of negligent
unclarified implications that Consciousness is in
implications that Consciousness is in
your brain and you are the counterpart
comes from you whatever permutations
these views might take um those little
assumptions that's how you maintain the
ownership of Consciousness you you don't
need to explicitly think Consciousness
is mine you just need to assume that
it's in in the body in your head that is
specially secondary to this body that's
placed in it you already appropriated it
that's all it takes and that's what's
already been done
that's already done to some extent yeah
either you're going to assume it that
it's like external it's out there they
can be measured or you going to assume
it that's inside internally either way
overshoot overshoot the mark undershoot
the mark Appropriations
there but that's what I mean like you
would be closer to contemplating
Consciousness rightly by correctly being
able to endure your moods without acting
out of or losing perspective of what
you've been absorbed but now kind of put
at the arms length but not denied it
that's closer to purifying your
Consciousness than you revolving around
your ideas of what Consciousness is and
then trying to tie the Loose Ends and so
on or find plausible explanations
purifying your consciousness of those
assumptions purifying consciousness of
those assumptions of being in me in
space exactly in time all of those
things because all anything that can be
noted anything that can be
manifested as how ever subtle idea that
might be is second to the existence of
the five Aggregates in other words it's
because of
them so it's second to the conscious
it's something you conscious of not
something you can measure conscious with
Consciousness with so you always arrive lateer to the
with so you always arrive lateer to the
party
basically that's what I mean you you
find when you start becoming uh PR well
start becoming aware of phenomena as
phenomena without making them too objective or too
without making them too objective or too
subjective seeing them to the extent
that they have
Arison one of the main traits of that
would be as I was saying in even in the
early writings before would be or you
find them already there you you don't
create them like even when you recollect
stuff is because it was already there
given
beforehand but the first step is to take
a step back well first step is to take a
step back so you realize in order to be
able to sustain the attitude of stepping
back internally without denying things
ahead of you you then have to start
restraining your behavior see practicing
virtue is a way of stepping back yeah
restraining your speech is a further way
of stepping back restraining your UNH
wholesome thoughts from intentionally
allowing them to proliferate and revolve
around sensuality ill will or
distraction is another form of
bracketing and stepping back and and and
and fortifying the stepping
back and then sure you can think about
these ideas while you have stepped back
those ideas will not pull you back into
the sense objects but if you just want
to bypass that whole development and
just get the satisfaction of craving to
clarifying these ideas that are
oppressing you you can spend your entire
life five lifetimes of clarifying ideas
and you won't be a step closer to
understand Consciousness getting the
definitions down yeah when you haven't
made that those phenomenon stand out
exactly through stepping back exactly
yeah